Kyle P. Costabile

kcostareal@gmail.com | (443) 602-5409 | Richmond, Virginia

SUMMARY

Senior Intellectual Property Manager with 8 years of experience in NASA's Technology Transfer Office, holding MBA and Engineering degrees. Expert in technology commercialization, patent licensing and negotiation, intellectual property strategy, product development, and managing a large portfolio of inventors and technologies across many different research disciplines. Patented inventor and accomplished co-founder of, and advisor to high-technology businesses.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Intellectual Property Manager

National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Langley Research Center

June 2023 – Present

- Manage the team responsible for the IP portfolio of NASA's Langley Research Center, including 150+ patents, 1000+ software programs, and license agreements totaling \$3.2 million.
- Negotiate, write, and execute patent licensing agreements, non-disclosure agreements (NDAs), material transfer agreements (MTAs), and cooperative research and development agreements (CRADAs)
- Solicit and evaluate invention disclosures, select technologies for patenting, manage patent prosecution, and develop and execute commercialization strategies
- Lead weekly meetings with and facilitate IP strategy of researchers and inventors in a broad spectrum of scientific disciplines and laboratory settings, including biomedical, materials, imaging, optics, sensors, and software.
- Lead weekly meetings with IP attorneys and provide regular program updates to leadership

Senior Licensing Executive

NASA Marshall Space Flight Center (Contracted through Acuity Edge, Inc.)

May 2018 - June 2023

- Manage the patent and license portfolio of Electronic Systems at NASA's Marshall Space Flight Center
- Leading licensor of technologies across NASA for FY20, FY21, and FY22 averaging 20 agreements per year
- Assist in training and managing a team of 3 junior licensing executives
- Evaluate invention disclosures, assess and select technologies for patenting, manage patent prosecution, and develop and execute commercialization strategies
- Lead marketing campaigns concerning NASA technologies available for licensing
- Manage NASA's pay.gov portal for license royalty collections
- Lead requirements developer for NASA Technology Transfer System (NTTS) Database

STARTUP EXPERIENCE

Founder, CTO

Icecap Sports Club

June 2023 – Present

- Led the development of a smart end cap and mobile application for lacrosse and hockey, including circuit board
 and battery design and sourcing, firmware, software, and database development, and machine learning/AI
 algorithm system setup and model training and deployment
- Secured a patent license agreement with an established sports equipment manufacturer
- Solicit and evaluate invention disclosures, select technologies for patenting, manage patent prosecution, and develop and execute commercialization strategies
- Lead weekly meetings with and facilitate IP strategy of researchers and inventors in a broad spectrum of scientific disciplines and laboratory settings, including biomedical, materials, imaging, optics, sensors, and software.
- Lead weekly meetings with IP attorneys and provide regular program updates to leadership

- Led the development of an innovative wearable technology integrating biometric tracking with real-time analytics, enhancing athletic performance.
- Architected and developed a cross-platform iOS/Android mobile application in Unity, enabling users to monitor and optimize their training using advanced motion and physiological data.
- Secured a patent license agreement, leveraging proprietary technology to create a unique, industry-leading product in sports performance tracking.
- Forged strategic collaborations and co-branded with [Major Sports Apparel Company], leading to expanded market reach, joint marketing initiatives, and retail distribution.
- Managed cross-functional teams across hardware, software, and data science, ensuring seamless product integration and go-to-market success.
- Raised [Funding Amount] in venture capital/seed funding and navigated the startup through early growth phases, including prototype development, user testing, and scaling production.

EDUCATION

Master of Business Administration

The University of Alabama | 3.71 | Concentration in Financial Risk Management

May 2019

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering

The University of Alabama | Minor in Social Innovation and Leadership

May 2018

PATENTS

Motion Analyzer for Sports Equipment

US Patent Number 11,779,822

Issued October 10, 2023

SKILLS

Intellectual property strategy, program & project management, cross-functional collaboration and leadership, patent law & IP fundamentals, product development, emerging technology, data science (Python, C++, C#, R), portfolio valuation, interpersonal skills, expert in Microsoft Office, machine learning, AI, medical technology